<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Authors on cedi.dev</title><link>https://cedi.dev/authors/</link><description>Recent content in Authors on cedi.dev</description><generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; {year} by Cedric Kienzler</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 17:15:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cedi.dev/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://cedi.dev/authors/cedi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cedi.dev/authors/cedi/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m Cedric and I am a Senior Software Engineer from Germany, working at Microsoft Azure.
I am interested in distributed systems and working at scale, specifially site reliability engineering and resiliency engineering.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am involved in somme stuff at the &lt;a href="https://ccc.de">Chaos Computer Club&lt;/a> where I led the Network Team at &lt;a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gulaschprogrammiernacht">GPN&lt;/a> (GPN-NOC) for two years. I also help with the builtup, planning (and a million other things) at various events trough the year, most notably the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaos_Communication_Congress">Chaos Communication Congress&lt;/a> at the end of every year.
During the pandemic - when the in-person events where unable to happen - I helped to build online services like &lt;a href="https://jitsi.rocks">jitsi.rocks&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://open-infrastructure.de">open-infrastructure&lt;/a>, and helped building the Kubernetes Infrastructure powering the the &lt;a href="https://rc3.world/2021/">rC3 - NOW HERE&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In my sparetime I love playing around with Kubernetes, Linux, Raspberry Pis, and various other technologies. I have a small Cluster of Pis at home, running &lt;a href="https://k3s.io">K3s&lt;/a>. I frequently re-compile the Kernel to try out different features or drivers on my Pis. I also have a &lt;a href="https://github.com/kubermatic/kubeone">KubeOne&lt;/a> cluster running in the Cloud, which I use to &lt;a href="https://cedi.dev/project/kubeone/">contribute bugfixes to KubeOne&lt;/a> and generally explore cloud native technologies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a passionate photographer and I have a small collection of analog cameras in 35mm film as well as 120 medium format which include a Hasselblad 500 c/m, a Leica M6 and a Canon A1.
Analoge photography for me is even more fun because I (can) develop film myself at home. I have a small dark-room setup with a enlarger for 35mm film.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>