<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>volunteer on cedi.dev</title><link>/tags/volunteer/</link><description>Recent content in volunteer on cedi.dev</description><generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; {year} by Cedric Kienzler</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/volunteer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Open Infrastructure</title><link>/project/open-infrastructure/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/project/open-infrastructure/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://open-infrastructure.de">Open-Infrastructure&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Infrastructure should be accessible for everyone.
except racists, homophobes, sexists, other scum.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Chaos Communication Congress Orga</title><link>/project/congress/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/project/congress/</guid><description>&lt;p>As part of the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/c3logistic">C3LOC&lt;/a> and the &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/c3bar">C3Bar&lt;/a> teams I helped organizing the logisticts, enabling other cruical teams of the congress orga to make the event happen. As part of the bar team, I helped the 14.000 attendees of the event staying hydrated during the day and drunk during the night.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>GPN NOC</title><link>/project/gpn/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/project/gpn/</guid><description>&lt;p>Oversaw and orchestrated the event organisation as the representative of the network team towards the event’s project management, including sponsor aquisation, budget management, and logistic for a highly reliable fault tolerant network for one of the largest hacker events in Germany.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• Lead a Team of 15 volunteers with various skills and levels to build and run the network infrastructure&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• Planned and controlled the budget&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• Acquired sponsors for network hardware and BGP interconnectivity&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• Wrote a SDN Controller in python3 using netconf, SNMPv3, and jinja2 for a heterogenous infrastructure to distribute the network in 5 lecture halls, two big hackcenters and the “OpenCodes” Art exhibition&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• Created extensive documentation during all stages of the project to ensure a reliable network&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• Worked together with 3rd party service providers to provide fiber connectivity as well as multi-homed BGP connectivity to the venue&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• Monitored the whole network infrastructure using Prometheus and Grafana&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>rC3 World Backend</title><link>/project/rc3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/project/rc3/</guid><description>&lt;p>Supported the &lt;a href="https://rc3.world/2021/world">rc3.world&lt;/a> backend team as part of the &lt;a href="https://infra.rc3.world">rC3 infrastructure team&lt;/a>, building and maintaining a Kubernetes Cluster as well as the corresponding multi-staged Elixir deployment required for the remote congress experience.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• Orchestrated a highly available Elixir Application using Kubernetes with Kustomize, Helm, and ArgoCD&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• Built a multi-staged GitLab CI Pipeline to compile, verify, an Elexir application, as well as the documentation, that powered the 2D world backend to the congress 2D world&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• Coordinated deployments in close collaboration with the leadership team (PL) of the event ensuring minimal disruption during for all users&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• Took 24h on-call responsibility during the whole event to resolve incidents as well as smaller issues&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>